Yannick Bériault . Jarvis Consulting

The first thing that attracted me into computer science were databases. Their potential for organizing and making sense of any type of data, as well as the impressive elegance presented by good code, something that I discovered during my training, are still aspects of the field that are really stimulating to me. I obtained a Certificate in computer science and am working on obtaining a second, advanced Certificate (both constituted of 30 credits). I have been working as a translator for many years before transitioning into software development.

Skills

Proficient: Java, Linux/Bash, RDBMS/SQL, Agile/Scrum, Git, JDBC

Competent: Vim, IntelliJ IDEA, JavaScript, HTML/CSS, Assembly language, Algorithmics and Mathematics for Computer Science, Docker, Spring framework

Familiar: C, C++, React, PHP, Laravel, Kubernetes, Jenkins, Haskell, Various binary encodings

Jarvis Projects

Project source code: https://github.com/jarviscanada/jarvis data eng YannickBeriault

Cluster Monitor [GitHub]: Implemented a monitoring agent that is used to automatically gather hardware as well as memory and CPU usage information on a system. It gathers usage info every minute, as long as the database instance is properly running. It was made using bash scripts and sql, on a virtual machine accessed through VNC viewer. It runs a PostgreSQL database inside a Docker container. It obtains its data using terminal commands, whose results it processes using a combination of simple bash commands like grep, cut and sed.

Core Java Apps [GitHub]: - Twitter App: Developed an app made to interact with Twitter's REST API in order to create, show and delete tweets. - JDBC App: Wrote a java program to enter customer info into a database and retrieve it. - Grep App: Implemented a simple version of the grep command.

Springboot App [GitHub]: Our trading team needed to replace their legacy trading platform with something more efficient, maintainable and scalable. The platform we built for them is a REST API meant to manage traders and their accounts, execute security orders and get information about quotes. The app was developed inside the Spring Boot framework with data persistence ensured by a postgresql database, connected through JDBC. It is meant to be run inside two docker containers, one for the app and one for the database.

Cloud/DevOps [GitHub]: This is a small project meant to deploy the trading app developed in the context of the so-called Springboot project inside a Kubernetes infrastructure where various instances of our application can be served through a load-balancer and to which can be added new instances when usage demands it, effectively auto-scaling our application while maintaining a sole Psql database instance with which the application instances can interact.

Highlighted Projects

ProjekRockola: Developed a command line based audio-player (no GUI) with elaborate smart playlist management. I decided to develop this program since no program gave me quite the smart playlist management experience I was looking for. It is written in Java, using javafx and JDBC. It makes use of an elaborate MySQL database, hosted locally. I use it every day.

Mainframe: Put together a simple GUI interface to manage various aspects of my personnal discipline. It is written solely in Java and uses simple text files for data persistence. It is an old project that will need to be totally revamped, but it has proven to be quite dependable. I also use it every day.

Professional Experiences

Software Developer, Jarvis (2022-present): I am tasked to implement and develop various applications that give me the opportunity to hone my skills with the technologies and techniques I learned in my training. I use languages such as bash, java and SQL, technologies such as virtual machines, the IntelliJ IDEA, Vim, Docker, Git and PostgreSQL, and techniques such as Agile/scrum and Gitflow.

Evaluator, Université du Québec à Montréal (2019-2021): I evaluated students' programs written in Java, C++ and assembly language. I also had to take the time to answer students' preoccupations and questions about their grades, being firm and understanding at the same time.

Translator, Amazon Europe Core (2017-2022): I translate products descriptions and internal documentations from English to French. I was happy to go from being employed from time to time to have access to almost all the contracts I could want through rigorous work and good evaluations from the organisation. Having the capacity to work with minimal information and try to still deliver the most appropriate result is also a skill I developed with this employer.

Education

Université du Québec à Montréal (2020-present), Advanced Certificate in Software Development, Computer Science - Cumulative average: 3.90/4.3

Université du Québec à Montréal (2018-2020), Certificate in Computer Science and Software Development, Computer Science - Diploma obtained - Cumulative average: 4.0/4.3

Miscellaneous

- Writing & Proofreading
- Problem solving & leadership
- Planning & decision making
- Artistic creation
- Creative writing
- Playing music
- Board games
- Geopolitics and humanities
- Bicycling and hiking
- Camping
- French (native)
- English (fluent)
- Spanish (fluent)
- German (beginner)